It just seems to me like there is probably some MBA things that need to be said here,
given the text exchanges the last day or so.
We did quite a bit of texting on it, so let's air some of that out.
Sorry about your pacers, buddy.
I don't need to talk about it. It's fine.
Hey, sorry TJ Warren got shut the fuck down.
TJ Warren. What a second half that guy had, huh?
Yeah. Yeah.
This bubble gameplay has been so surprisingly good.
I agree.
It's been great to watch.
I agree, and the number of really good, I mean, well-played games and then good finishes,
you know, like the close games versus blowout quotient is way better than the normal season.
You know, it seems to me, and it may just be because of the compression time,
because these guys, I mean, I think that they live 24-7 basketball during this time of the season anyway,
but, like, this is especially just...
What else are you going to do?
We'll get a lot of haircuts.
I mean, maybe the pressure of the pandemic is, like, focusing all of them in some implicit way as well, you know?
I mean, they're going out, they're playing hard.
Like, these are good games, so...
This is also where the social justice directive that the league has taken up, I think, has made it...
No, I feel like players feel like they're playing for more than just basketball, too, which makes a difference.
Yeah. They respect the commissioner.
They probably respect most of the coaches.
Like, yeah, it's like a good relationship that they all have with each other, unlike the NFL.
I was just going to say, like, who could imagine a league like that?
I noticed that last night after the Lakers game in LeBron's postgame.
You could tell his response to the questions were about the historical moment, not about the game, right?
It was like, it's good for us to go out in a time like this.
In other words, like, he sees his role, and I don't think he's alone in this,
but, I mean, he sees his role in a postgame interview as not being a representative of the Lakers primarily,
but as being a sort of spokesperson for social justice.
He's done that from the beginning of the bubble.
It's like he, you know, in the first couple interviews, he was asked questions about the games,
and then he completely ignored them, and was talking about justice for Breonna Taylor, right?
Right, right, right.
That's definitely cool, but I feel like, at least for me, if I was exhausted after a game,
I'd be like, shit, what are my talking points about racism?
I forgot my good, like, points I had in my head.
I know.
I mean, they don't, they don't, we don't think about that very often.
The postgame interview, it's like, just think of it, I mean,
I obviously never played anywhere near a level like that,
but the times after I had, like, a hard couple of hours of basketball,
it's like, ask me a question, I'd be like, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
I don't have anything going on to say.
Racism is bad.
Racism sucks.
Yeah.
Shit.
You know.
Water.
That's impressive, man.
Yeah.
I mean, could you imagine Jordan doing that, though?
Yeah, well.
Well, he'd just be like, well, they all buy sneakers, or whatever his quote was.
Republicans buy sneakers.
Racists buy Jordans, too.
I mean, I'm not going to alienate them.
I'm just, I mean, just the way that James has cultivated himself as a figure in and beyond sport is, I mean, it's just really impressive.
Well, that's what, I mean, I think I said that before, but that was one of the takeaways for me of the Jordan Bulls miniseries that, you know, was like, if there was a debate between LeBron and Jordan, I think there is no longer one.
Like, LeBron is a way better figure of, you know, just in all facets.
For sure.
He's like a decent human.
Yeah.
An actual role model.
Yes.
That's right.
Now, let's just pray.
Not a sociopath.
Let's pray that LeBron doesn't have any skeletons.
You know, that would be the worst.
He gets canceled somewhere in the next couple years.
God.
I know.
That would, that would, that would.
But, I mean, think of the pressure on him.
Because, do you remember, Nathaniel, I talked to you about this.
You remember this.
But remember after the China thing, I was like, I was down on Harden and LeBron because they were sort of apologists for the NBA and that.
And I can't remember who made the comment, but I thought it was a really great comment and it changed my mind on it.
Where they were like, you're asking this guy who's, you know, MVP, perennial MVP candidate of the NBA and does so much stuff to, like, know everything about every global political issue.
And this is just one that he doesn't know about.
And give him a fucking break.
And I was like, that's a really good point.
You know, I was like, yeah, I kind of am being a jerk by getting pissed at him for not taking a stand against, you know, humanitarian abuses in China.
Like, come on.
It gives it that vibe of a giant, like, giant life-size appropriation machine.
You know, it's just eating all difference.
I don't think you can discount that reading of Hegel either.
I mean, that is sort of more of the traditional reading, I think, like, as opposed to the people I've been dealing with.
But, you know, the totalizing impulse is there.
It runs all throughout.
It's just, again, the way I've been reading it is that it's not that that totalizing impulse is, like, celebrated.
It's more that it's just, it's schematized, right?
So, the shift to absolute spirit is not, like, finding joy in this totalizing monster.
It's really just a recognition of that impulse and kind of, like, for me, at least, it functions as a warning about that impulse rather than, like, yay, go appropriation, you know?
Yeah, yeah.
Although, in all fairness, it is a, appropriation is a development.
It's progressive.
So, it is kind of a yay.
I mean, it's not, like, I mean, he doesn't have to be a fan of it in order to see it as a progressive advancement.
And the need he feels, as many do and did, to distinguish his thing from other things.
I mean, that's a hugely important element of it, I think.
And that's very related to what, to your diss project, right?
Like, that I think a key part of this now, not just a sort of ancillary part from which to begin, a key part of this is the need to have something that's distinct from the other thinkers before me.
It's part of what lends it that, like, well, not that stuff, you know?
Right.
Well, there's so many pressures that create that scholarly move, especially today.
Sure, sure.
I mean, in Hegel's time, it was obviously strongly felt.
But today, I mean, that's the way you brand yourself.
It's like, it's an unavoidable move to some extent.
And that's the thing that I find problematic in Barad, is that, you know, her whole idea is difference, an ontological difference, where basically it's grounded in this relationality.
But she's so invested in making what I see as basically arbitrary cuts away from Butler and away from Foucault and away from deconstruction, even away from Niels Bohr, who's like her boy.
And it's like, why do you need to do that?
Yeah, that's the same vibe I had when I read, like, the Harmon and the object-oriented stuff, was I was just like, it just seemed so committed to a branding operation that I was just kind of, eh.
No, I mean, I get it.
Like, you have to do it.
It's just how you do that, how you stylize that.
I don't agree with that, though.
I mean, that to me, for me at least, that was the project of the last book and certainly will be for this one, is like, I don't think that you have to do it.
I mean, look, in all fairness, yes, you have, at some level, you're not making everything indistinct, but I also do think that you don't have to, for instance, one of the things that's crucial for me is I'm not going to invent new words.
I'm not going to have an ambient rhetoric or I'm not going to have a new, like, there's no, there's no new terminology for me, right?
Like, and that's been an important one for me all along, is I don't want to, it's like, you know how everyone does that as a way of summarizing their thing, like, rhetoricity or, you know, what's Diane's, I can't even, was it rhetoricity?
It's rhetoricity, yeah, that's it.
Yeah, okay.
So, but again, like, each of those, those are attempts to sort of, like, slightly distinguish and for me it's always been like, no, I'm going to use the same terminology that everybody else uses so that there's nothing distinctive, you know, at that level that you can point to and say, well, Muckelbauer's theory of X, you know.
Right. It's easy to see why people, it's easy to see why people do it, though.
Of course.
I mean, it, it, it rubs me the wrong way, but, like, in terms of, like, the dynamics of the institution and the publishing industry, it's almost difficult not to at least attempt some of those moves because, I mean, look at Barad.
I mean, as annoying as all that stuff is, that's the reason why we're talking, that's why we're talking about her.
That's right, that's right.
But that's where, I mean, that's where, like, taking the, this is where the Deleuze becoming imperceptible is really interesting to me, is.
It's not a question of, it doesn't necessarily have to be.
So all of those sort of, what, because those pressures are kind of external pressures, right?
They're not the pressures from the thinking.
They're pressures from institutions.
They're pressures from, you know, all those, not pressures, but forces that induce that.
And there's, I mean, it doesn't seem to me that there's anything about the thinking that requires that.
There are things about an individual who writes, you know, in an institution in ecology that wants to get, again, recognition that requires a distinctiveness or a branding of some kind.
But I think there's a lot to be said for, and I, hopefully I'm going to try to say it, you know, for, like, for the indistinguishability, for the ambiguity, uncertainty, whatever terminology of, like, not knowing how my thing is different from, you know, everyone else's.
And really thinking that it's not, you know, other than that it's, like, my name's on the book and not someone else's name.
So, and even that's not necessary.
Now, I get that, but, like, most people, even some of the better thinkers are not that self-conscious.
Like, if, so, I would, I would, I don't know, I would challenge a little bit that idea of, like, the external pressure because it's completely internalized in Barad, right?
I mean, the, she's an effect of biopower rather than a commentator on it.
You know what I mean?
Yeah.
So.
Well, maybe I'm wrong to call it simply external, but I'm just saying it does seem to me imaginable, or at least I've tried that in my work of, like, pursuing, for me, the indistinguishability between my thinking and the thing that I'm reading, for instance, such that when you read it, you don't really know.
I mean, I learned that from Derrida to a certain extent.
But, look, Derrida's branded himself quite well, right?
Like, Difference and, you know.
So, I mean, I don't know.
Maybe it's going to turn out that I'm just, at the end of the day, I'm going to be wrong about this one.
But I think it's, as a project, it's, at least to me, a more interesting one of, like, I don't want it to be recognized.
Or, rather, it doesn't matter, maybe.
It's not that I don't want it to be.
But it doesn't matter, you know.
I mean, what I find tiresome about the constant branding is then you're, like, swimming in, I feel like I'm swimming in terms with a little R's and T's, you know, next to them.
That, you know, that they're hard to mobilize.
I, one of the difficulties I had writing early on was trying to mobilize these terms.
And because they were so specifically attached to specific teacher or to specific scholars that I felt like I had to be faithful to the thing that they were doing.
But the more generic concepts were just far more pliable.
And I do find something different with, like, I mean, a lot of the terms that Derrida, you know, that we consider to be Derridian are not positive concepts in that, like, they're Derrida's idea or concept of this thing.
But they're more, like, dynamics or structures or phenomenon that are undergoing that Derrida just thinks through, which, like, then becomes invitations for other people to think through as well without it being more or less faithful to Derrida's conception of the thing.
And, in fact, the one thing that Derrida resisted the most was turning something into deconstruction into a thing or a method or a process, like, whatever else it is.
Like, that – insofar as he branded himself, he was the – it's not a thing, branding, right?
It's not a product.
But that's also – I mean –
Yes.
Right?
Like, I mean, so, for instance, he didn't stop talking about deconstruction.
He talked endlessly about deconstruction.
Now, what he always said about deconstruction, not a word, not a concept, not – you know, like, he always – but it was – I mean, again, that's to me – I think back of –
I think back of – Deleuze makes a distinction, I can't remember where the Deleuze – the Beckett-Joyce distinction, right?
That on the question of identification, which is what we're talking about here, identifying something, like, that Joyce went the route of multiplication, which is just – I'm just going to put so much shit in Finnegan's Wake, you know, that it's going to be incomprehensible.
Whereas Beckett – and this was – Deleuze is more interested in this, and I am as well – Beckett went the route of subtraction.
Like, I'm just going to take everything out so that there's nothing, you know, I'm going to do an entire play that is a gesture or something, you know what I mean?
Like, there's going to be nothing – like, nothing will happen, nothing is going to – you know, so it's – those two different approaches.
Again, both of them are interested in problematizing, complicating the movements of identification, but they're really different styles, right?
Like, they're really different comportments to the project of complicating distinction or identification or recognition, again, it's – you know.
Well, on the face of it, you would think Deleuze would attach himself to Joyce, right?
Because that's more of a – that's more of an obvious multiplicity.
That's exactly right.
Right, but he's more interested in the subtractions of Beckett, which – I mean, when you actually look at Deleuze, that it does make sense that he would go to Beckett there.
But it takes a little bit of work.
It does.
It's not immediately – especially, you know, the proliferation that is Anti-Oedipus and Thousand Plateaus, right?
There's just such a profusion of different kinds of concepts.
But I agree with you because I think of it like an interesting Kafka.
Kafka is like one of the least interesting humans, right?
I mean, in terms of his life, right?
Masochism, right?
I mean, he always – frequently will go the – I mean, one of my favorite phrases in my invention book was – it's – the first time I mentioned Deleuze and Guattari is I introduced them by saying,
as the great thinkers of confinement, Deleuze and Guattari.
And that's one of my favorite phrases because it's like that's it.
They are thinkers of confinement.
Like, you want to talk about movement?
They are thinkers of movement, but it's intensive movement.
It's not – it's not – you know, because once you enter into this sort of identification, recognition types of movement, then it becomes the most you can do is just invent massively – you know, like go Finnegan's Wake, right?
That's the – Finnegan's Wake is kind of end point, I think, for –
It's sort of the brain yes of the ass, right?
Right, yeah.
That's all that you can do.
Right.
See, that to me just makes me think that most of these people that are explicitly anti-dialectical, I understand why they make those decisions and why Deleuze and Foucault make those kind of cuts.
But that's where, again, like the distinguishing between Deleuze and Hegel with that comment you just made about confinement, that makes it harder for me to think that distinction.
Because Hegel's obviously a thinker of confinement as well, right?
I mean, it's not just a multitude – it's not just everything's moving all at once.
He's thinking about, you know, explicit structures and the way they affect us.
And, I mean, again, it's way more explicitly phenomenological.
But the way that Becoming is articulated seems to be so similar in a sense.
I have to think about that one.
I mean, it doesn't immediately ring true for me, but I'm not going to discount it either.
I mean –
Well, it's like Foucault is also, like, you know, the anti-dialectical thinker par excellence.
And, like, I basically just figured that out, that he explicitly positioned himself that way.
Because in my readings of him, I'm like, I associate him with Butler, with Hegel.
And he didn't.
So I'm like, well, why didn't he?
I don't know.
It's still something I have to figure out, but a little more.
It seems to me to be a matter of what produces the confinement, right?
And that, I mean, my orientation to Deleuze and those in that tradition, it's that confinement tends to be a byproduct of appropriation of between differences, right?
Like, an aggressive appropriation as opposed to an appropriation that's only made possible because of self-alienation.
So the confinement is the confinement or the stifling confinement of the one that must then self-alienate and reappropriate.
And that's just a different kind of confinement than, you know, the specific, you know, trajectory and angle and force and qualitative differences between two – one force that appropriates another, right?
Like, the confinement produced by the particular intersection of an appropriation is one kind of confinement as opposed to what I would take to be the much more claustrophobic confinement of a –
this is where I want to go back to think of – this is where I'm not being generous to Hegel again because I think of it as like this overabundant self-presence that has to self-alienate.
But that renders the self as a point which, again, I can do it seven times out of ten, but not ten out of ten when I'm reaching out.
Well, so, I mean, my – the thing that I'm thinking as you're talking there, Nathaniel, is like maybe this is just too simple, but there's a way in which – a baseline way in which –
I mean, this is the move that you make actually, Nate, in your proposal, the revised version of the proposal where you're a little more generous to Casey and Diane.
Again, by not making them ontological thinkers but making them ethical thinkers, that there's a sense in which, you know, maybe that's the sort of delusian orientation.
It's like given whatever sort of ontological circumstance, Kafka as a person doesn't move, you know, or the masochist as a figure doesn't move.
And that the claim is more about how to live, right?
How to live in a circumstance as opposed to, I don't know, like Hegel's – this is not – you know, it's spirit.
Spirit is not – he seems kind of in some ways maybe uninterested in how to live, you know.
At this juncture and, you know, in this book.
But that question is not really on the table for – this is just like, well, look, life is this voracious appropriation machine and I'm just going to lay out for you how it works.
As distinct from, you know, potentially the delusian orientation was, well, given that, here are ways to live that are less contributing to the voracious appropriation machine or at least attempt to interrupt it in some ways.
Yeah.
I think that's absolutely right and, I mean, it's – that's the reason why you can couple, like, Nietzsche and delus, maybe even put Foucault in there is because they're actually interested in modes of living that are other than resentment or whatever.
Right.
Whereas for Hegel, ethics is not really a choice or it's – rather ethics is incorporated into this system of appropriation.
So, again, like, even if there's – as nuanced as delus's or Nietzsche's ideas about that ethical intervention are, for Hegel, that's still – right, there's no real way out of the – like you guys are saying, the appropriation machine.
So, when you think there's a better mode of life, it still falls back into this movement of simplicity or negation or whatever, you know.
Well, this is where, like, the notion of better just functions very different for delus and Hegel as well because for Hegel, like, the notion of better is completely governed by, like, the transcendent progression of absolute spirit, in which case there is no choice.
It's just machinating, right?
But the notion of better is also problematic for delus at all as well because there is no transcendent metric by which to say better or worse.
And, like, when I was saying before about this different sense of confinement, it's like, no, no, no.
Given this intersection of forces, which produces a confinement, right, one idiosyncratic set of confinements that allow for different modes of life.
And then the ethical question is not, like, make that life better or worse, but experiment with the kinds of life that that confinement makes possible.
Right.
That's, to me, the distinction.
So, it's not about choosing a better form of life or finally figuring it out.
It's like, no, given the field, you know, the mandate is to experiment.
For those thinkers, the mandate is see what you can do.
And one possibility might be transforming the field, right?
Like, but that's nothing you're never going to know.
And you're, you know.
Right.
Well, then, the question for me, then, is why can't we be, like, scope, just even broader scope.
Like, why can't we be generous to everyone?
Like, why do I have the impulse to glom onto Hegel rather than delus?
Why do you guys, why are you at least slightly more generous with delus?
Like, what engendered these decisions?
And why am I so invested in, you know, attaching myself to one rather than the other?
I mean, is that just, like, kind of.
It is the same.
And to me, it's the same question as making the distinctions about the people that you're reading and not reading.
Like, you know, for me, the project, I mean, it's an interesting idea because what happens if I try to, that's why you should, I mean, in a sense, go after delus, but also go after Hegel as well.
Right.
But think of an interesting way of doing it, not just the sort of, like, okay, yes, everyone says this is a voracious machine-like thing, but maybe, and that's in many ways I feel like what I'm struggling with is how do we understand the projects of these other folks like delus, like Foucault?
I mean, as you pose the question there of, I always saw him as part of this, you know, this lineage, but he didn't see himself as part of that lineage, and why not?
What was up for him?
And even if it turns out that what you discover is, well, because he had a kind of poor reading of Hegel that was based on these traditional notions of totalitarian statehood, come up with a better one, right?
Yeah.
Come up with better, and to me, this sounds kind of like a better one, which is, given the ontological condition of negation, experiment with other possibilities.
Right.
Yeah.
You know?
But this is, I mean, my question is this is, I see where, I mean, forget about it as a mandate, I just see how experimentation is possible within the ontological field.
That Deleuze sets up, right?
Yeah.
Because, I mean, I don't even know what it would mean to experiment with it.
Like, there's no, like, one of my fundamental questions has been, can there be right or wrong turns in here?
Or, like, just to make it more radical, can there be turns, right?
Right.
This just seems like it's a straight road.
Well, that's the dead end question that you asked before.
Yeah.
Are there dead ends?
Like, do people do it wrong?
Whereas I would even, you know, intensify your earlier claim about, you know, changing the field as a possible mode of experimentation with a kind of confinement and not knowing whether you're doing it or not.
I would go radically the other direction and say, you're changing the field no matter what you do and how you, you're experimenting with it regardless, irregardless, it's now officially a word.
Regardless of what you do.
Because you said it?
No, because the OED adopted it.
They decided enough dumb fuckers have started using it thinking it was a word that we've got to.
We'll just put it in there.
We've just got to put it in there, yeah.
I mean, it's a big fucking book.
What difference does another word do it?
Yeah, he gives a shit.
But, like, the field can't help but be remade.
And it's, like, it would be very difficult to imagine what a straight line would look like in that.
Like, I think maybe that's the biggest difference.
I think it's difficult to imagine a straight line within a Deleuzian ontology.
And it's very difficult to imagine a turn within Hegel's field.
Yeah, I mean, what Hegel offers me specifically for my project is, like, just an anti-utopianism.
So, what I sense in Barad and even in Butler and people that kind of react against some of the, what I guess, fatalism sort of of Hegel is what I want to lean into.
Because it just seems, I don't know, either truer or more pragmatic or something.
Because what, the moves that Butler tries to make away from Hegel ends up simply, again, like, not, I feel like I keep emphasizing the appropriation machine in a bad way.
But, like, for me, it functions as a warning.
Like, every time you think you're transforming the field or whatever, every time you have an inclination or a sense that something is being transformed or that you're operating on the side of progressive change.
Which I'm not saying, like, Deleuz does or anyone.
But people like Barad are invested in those kind of moves.
It's like, for Hegel, that's, it's, it's both untenable and, like, kind of a necessary reaction to the dynamics of negation.
You know, so, like, that, that reach for progress is both necessary and impossible.
It's that constant movement.
And I can see how that's, like, not attractive for people.
I mean, like, it's not, I don't think it's attractive for most people even in everyday life to think that everything is sort of incorporated under a system of negation.
It's like, that's not something that, like, it's not like a motto that everyone runs around with.
But, um, I don't know if there is a progressivism here, though.
Is there not?
I mean, like, everything is moving toward the absolute consciousness of, of manifestation and consciousness of, of God.
So, like, I do get, like, you know.
Artificial intelligence, baby.
That's Hegel's.
When Hegel plays it out, there it is.
Predicted it, yeah.
I mean, the bubble that is getting popped is that, you know, people think that they can produce progress that is different from, you know, the sort of downward slope.
Like, they can be the one that saves the thing or they can be the one that diverts it onto the right track.
And they've made, you know, following their, their plan is better than the other one.
And, like, you know, Hegel's just like, like, Drake.
God's plan.
Yeah.
Yeah, you can't get away from it.
I know, but.
Go ahead, man.
Go ahead.
It's just, like, I see that reading and I, again, like, I think that that's fair and viable.
It's just, for me, absolute spirit doesn't signal progress in that, in a traditional sense of, like, getting better.
Absolute spirit maybe is better for the philosopher.
It's not, it's not better for life or for people.
It's just simply a, it's a, it's a progression in thinking.
But there's no, again, there's no comfort.
There's no, you can't rest in that space.
That's when you actually, that's when you have to invent and experiment.
That's, to me, when experimentation happens in Hegel.
Once you reach that reflexive point where you're like, oh, this is actually all a movement of self.
There's no outside reality separate from me.
So now I can start playing around, right?
Like, so that's when the play starts happening in Hegel.
Okay, because what I was going to, because what I was going to ask you a moment ago, which I think is a very, I mean, it's a question for your project and for where you are right now.
Because here's the thing, I'm totally sympathetic to your motivations.
They're ones that I share, which is the, you know, the desire to smack down, you've heard me rant about like the desire to smack down the kind of more or less implicit, sometimes it's just explicit, but the moralism of, you know, most scholarship that we read of like, and the desire to smack that down.
For me, for instance, folks like Barad and particularly the new materialists coming in the wake of Barad, they're just low-hanging fruit.
They're just like, they're just not very smart.
And so I just, and so to me, I just don't even really, I mean, I think that you're right.
I just don't care because I think for me, one of the things that shifted at a certain point or not, it's not, it's not an age development for me.
It's actually, I have to get past that desire or impulse to smack down the implicit moralism.
Because at the end of the day, the question that matters the most to me is what am I going to make, right?
And like, what, what can I make, like, what kind of machine or what kind of thing can I generate?
And at a certain level, smacking down the, the sort of poor imitators is not really making, is not really making anything.
It's just.
Right.
Well, I, I agree.
I mean, that's why, like, for certain figures, I mean, not to get into my prospectus, whatever, or my project totally, but like, that's why.
That's all we're talking about.
Why don't you?
Well, I know.
I know.
I just, I just don't want to like, I don't want to be the totalizing person.
I don't want to embody Hegel in these conversations.
Yeah, but Nate, you didn't do this.
Nathaniel and I did this to you, okay?
All right, all right.
We took your fucking prospectus and we're like, we're going to organize a goddamn video thing around this whole, around your prospectus.
So it's your fault.
Okay.
All right.
But so, like, the certain figures, I completely agree with your, that diagnosis.
Like, like, that's for sure low-hanging fruit.
And I wasn't even really interested when I was writing those paragraphs.
Now, when I got to the more generous, we can cut that.
When I got to the more.
Get all of your disses out right now so we can, we know where to look when we're cutting everything out.
Fucking.
No, no, see, see, when we get, when I get to the more generous readings, I actually think I got, I can get good productive readings out of.
Because I'm reading them like primary sources.
I'm reading, I'm reading like a secondary source of Barad, which that's when it's like, okay, this is not really.
No one's gaining anything out of this.
But the better, some of the better rhetorical theorists in our field, you can read them like you would read Barad or Hegel or whoever.
So I think there's still, you can have productive commentary with them.
Yeah.
I want you to come after me.
Come after the invention book.
I would be, I'm being totally serious.
Like, if there's something there, I'm not saying you got, I mean, but I'm just saying, like, so as the sort of Deleuze rep in the field, you know, like, I'd be interested in that.
Because, because it's, it's, it really is interesting to me.
And I do, like I said, I share the impulse.
And I just, for me, I never wanted to, so for instance, earlier versions of the invention book, like the dissertation version, were much more polemical.
And a lot of the stuff that, there's residues of stuff on B-sicker in there and a couple of other things where I just kind of took them out or toned them down.
Because I realized, for me, I was like, actually, it's that move that I want to try to forestall.
And it's the move of saying, I'm not them, right?
I'm not, or the thinking I'm doing is not aligned with that.
And what became interesting to me was, and it was early on in the diss writing process, and it was the, oh God, the audience addressed, audience, the Eid and Lunds folks.
Invoked, yeah.
Right, so those two, and that's, I mean, I just find that to be an insipid and a perfect example of this kind of liberal ethos that masquerades itself as a kind of intellectual project.
And it, I mean, I, honestly, I just remember reading that for the first time and being like, this is so frustrating and angering to me.
Not just the piece itself, but also how it was taken up is like, oh, this is a wonderful example of inclusion and all this kind of stuff.
And I really want to smack it down.
And the first chapter that I wrote, the chapter, I can't remember which one it was, but I ended up, so I started off with a kind of polemical takedown of that.
And as I wrote through it and continued on, it ended up revisiting some of that, and where Eid and Lunsford ended up having kind of like anticipated my objections and done, and sort of done something to prevent me, prevent those kinds of objections.
And I was like, wow, this is a way weirder space to be in where I no longer dislike that progressive liberalism because it actually has hinges that I believe they probably didn't ever think of.
Right.
But they're there.
I mean, I didn't just invent them, you know.
And so it was this interesting moment of, oh, my God, I don't know who Eid and Lunsford are anymore.
And therefore, I don't know who I am in relation to them anymore.
And now, this is precisely the productive space.
And so it required the polemical, but it also required the undermining of the polemical using them, right, to get into that space of where what I just said mirrors what you were saying about absolute spirit is the place where the shit can happen, right?
Where the sort of pure contingency of multiplicity, whatever, that was my sort of experience working through it.
And, I mean, who knows how you're going to go through it, but it's just an interesting move.
When you get to that thinking of indistinction, and it's still, at least for me, it's not like I got there and I lived there and I'm now there and it's a fucking, you know, put up a homeowner sign or something.
It's like, it's always work, in a sense, to get into that space where I don't think I'm distinguishing myself from something.
But I always see it as a draw.
It's like, how can I use this thing, and even our interactions like this, how can I use this thing in order to induce in me that disillusion of desire for recognition, in a sense, you know?
So I'm just thinking about the different ways of producing that movement.
And it sounds like it, at least for you, starts with the polemical.
It did.
What you've done is, like, you do the polemical work, and then you, like, do it against the strongest version of the target that you can create.
And then once you've rendered the indistinction through the work of the polemical, you subtract the polemicism and attribute the positive value back to this indistinct, you know?
Well, because it really does get to the point where it's like, oh, fuck, all those things that I said that got me here don't really make sense anymore.
Given the generous reading that I've done and sort of, you know, been forced to do, that given the generous reading, the ungenerous stuff that got me there doesn't make sense.
What about, like, another way of doing it without subtracting the polemics?
Allow, like, start with the polemical and then let it intensify to the point where it becomes indistinguishable from the polemicized.
And then you're in this fun, like, you can be in this very fun place of almost, like, ironic mania where you can't tell the one from the other.
And, like, just as a pedagogical move for the reader, like, to be able to follow the, you know, this absolute distinction into this almost manic indistinction.
That's what I was going to say.
Yeah, like, the polemic and the indistinction, I think, at least under the Hegelian or maybe the Zizekian comportment, those don't have to be separate moments, right?
Because, I mean, someone like Zizek especially, he's so polemical, he's just striking people down, right?
Thinkers after thinkers, just, this is what they missed.
This is how they absolutely missed the point.
But that, it comes back to his own project in some way.
So, that's like, he's almost, he's chastising everybody, including himself in that picture.
So, it's almost like the polemic is just variegated to this point of, like, at a certain point, you don't really know the target.
It's like, we're all the target.
Everybody's the target.
Myself is the target, you know.
But that movement would have to be, that movement would have to, it couldn't be dismissive, right?
It would have to be a polemic that could, that could never arrive at the moment of dismissal.
Because the, the more it tried to render to the distinction that can be dismissed, the more that distinction becomes indistinct, right?
That would, I mean, to me, that's what would, that, the movement couldn't, the movement couldn't be like, dismiss this, dismiss this, dismiss this.
Right, it can't, yes.
Well, I mean, it can be, but that's going to short circuit the, the sort of generous indistinguishability moment.
I mean, it's going to make that.
But I think of, like, in, it's the chapter that I'm thinking about, so it was the audience chapter in the invention book.
And I start off with, like, you know, the popular phrase of one must, the writer should consider their audience when they write.
And I go through a little bit of, like, that is a meaningless, worthless statement.
Like, it doesn't say anything, and yet everybody thinks it's this really important message, but what could it actually mean?
But by the end, I just fully endorsed that slogan as being, well, you know, that's, that's the lesson that I've learned, is that the audience, the audience, or the writer must consider their audience when they write.
And that, that, that sentence now has so many possible senses to it, and is so diffuse and amorphous as to not offer any solace or comfort or even direction.
And that, to me, was, that was the interesting thing of the, the change in the sense of this slogan that, you know, people say all of the time from one of, think about other people when you're composing to, like, you know, whatever the fuck, you know, this kind of massive indistinguishability as the space for invention or whatever.
But, but, but the, the important movement in that is that, you know, the slogan at the beginning becomes, like, a maxim, like, run this machine, right?
And then by the time it becomes a slogan again, it's like, it becomes a provocation for having to, like, think, and you don't know because it's inhabited, taken on so many things, you don't know where it's going to take you.
Let's read, let's read, let's read that one for, let's read that chapter for the next time, because, I mean, I haven't read it in 15 years, but I, I just remember the writing of that, and it really, because that's the Eden Lunsford stuff as well.
And so we'll see if it still is, still remain, if I got all the polemics out.
But that's what that chapter was, was it ended up being this, like, slogan that at the beginning is an untenable slogan that by the end is, like, the only thing that you can possibly say about writing, you know?
Right, yeah.
I'd be interested to hear your guys' responses to the movement of that chapter.
Yeah, and I mean, the movement from endorsement to complication to kind of provisional endorsement to complication, I mean, that's what interests me, and that's sort of what at least Zizek's version of Hegel provides, is that there's no simple endorsement of a mode of thinking or a paradigm or whatever.
And that's what I react against in the Barads and people like that, is that there's one singular endorsement of this mode without a constant kind of turning over of that mode of thinking.
So it's like, that's the main thing for me, is like, if you're going to endorse anything, it's the process of interrogating your own endorsements.
Right, the problem is the dogmatism.
Yeah, yeah.
Even if the dogmatism is not, like, strident and, like, you know, shouting at the front of a crowd, like, it's still implicit in the thinking that, yeah, I mean, I agree with you.
I mean, that's where, for me, very influential for me coming to Deleuze, because the first thing that I ever read was the Foucault, because I'd spent my first semester of graduate school, I just read everything by Foucault that was translated at the time.
And then Foucault, it was my second semester of master's program, where I read the Foucault intro to Antioedipus, right?
And the whole message of that preface is, this is the book that's an introduction to the anti-fascist life, and recognizing the ways in which all the little molecular fascisms that comprise the directions of our thinking.
So that informed so much of how I went into Deleuze, because I was like, well, that's exactly the project that interests me, is, I mean, we don't have to call it fascist, we can call it dogmatic, as you're saying, or earlier I was calling this, you know, moral, the moral high ground or whatever.
But it is, it is that, right?
Like, that sense of, here's the thing to do.
But it's interesting to me, because what appeals to you is not a kind of wavering quality, it's actually a dogmatic commitment to non-dogmatism.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
Like, and, but that's not necessarily a contradiction, I mean, it's only a contradiction logically, like, I see that as, like, this sort of insistent point.
But that's where I'm going to come back for you, in terms of your project, is, like, what are you going to make, right?
Like, so I get how that's fun to smack, not fun, I don't want to, I don't want to diminish it at all.
Right.
I get the draw and the appeal of the smackdown, and I would say, like, for me, speaking and, like, in class, that's 90% of what I do, is the smackdown of the thing that thinks it's found the answer.
But for me, at least, writing has always been, at least academic writing has always been, I don't want to write that shit up.
It's just, it feels gross to me to write that up.
I'm always interested in writing up something that's the next step, right?
Like, so, what do we make now?
Part of the fun of the experiment is, you know, because you don't propose the dogma in place of the dogma that you're smacking down,
or that if there is one there, it's just the dogmatic adherence to smacking down the dogma is, like, I mean, that could be an interesting line of flight just to see what happens when the criticism isn't for the sake of some, you know, on the horizon, you know, dogmas.
Like, what happens when that becomes, what can relentless criticism and negation do?
That's Adorno, that's negative dialectic.
Right.
I mean, it may, by the way, I'm not saying it's not Hegel and it's not Zizek, I'm just saying, like, that's, to me, that was the thing that I got from Adorno's negative dialectic, is just like, oh my God, this is just relentless criticism, you know?
And then criticism of the criticism, and then criticism of the criticism of the, you know, like, there's no sublation, there's no off-hebong.
In his terms, the sublation or off-hebong was the positive moment of growth, right, or progress, and that's what, he's effectively trying to take that moment out of Hegel, right?
So, that there's, and it's just, man, I mean, it's cool, it's really cool.
I mean, from my perspective, that's going to make something.
There's no way that that can't make something, but I don't know what it is, right?
And that could be the fun of the experience.
Which is okay.
You could call it a method of reading.
Well, that makes it fun.
You could call it a method of interpretation, but yeah, I mean, that's the basic, right?
The relentless suspicion of the movement of discourse, of conceptuality, right?
The constant, like, turning over of your own propositions, seeing what they do in different contexts, seeing if they still function the way you wanted to at first, right?
So, that ruthless or relentless self-consciousness, I mean, to me, that's, I don't see that anywhere.
So, at least in terms of a comportment, right?
If I'm offering a comportment, that is something.
No, no, no.
Here's another way of putting it.
Putting it in some of the language that you had earlier is, like, you, what you really liked about, what you really like about Hegel is that he doesn't offer you the solace of rest, right?
That there isn't any place where you can be like, all right, we're better now because everything is under the process of the self-alienation.
And that's precisely the bubble that you like to pop is that people just want to find somewhere to have, like, to rest.
And if anything, if there is a moralism, for you, it seems to be like rest is, one, the figure of rest is just not on the table, right?
It's impossible.
And it's not desirable either.
That would be death, right?
Right.
Exactly.
So, the only response to completely short-circuit the desire to rest, to find, you know, the good plateau is relentless criticism.
You know what one of your targets then should be?
Because I like this.
I mean, this sounds cool.
Like, one of your targets should be, think of, like, the Latour and the Kate Hales, like, a decade ago.
And there seems to be this kind of giving up of the so-called hermeneutics of suspicion because it didn't really pan out to get us.
And you're like, yeah, it wasn't fucking suspicious enough, right?
Exactly, yeah.
You know, I mean, that's, you know, your claim is exactly the opposite of theirs, of that it didn't go far enough.
And so, instead of giving that up and siding with the making of stuff, instead it's like, no, let's double down on the suspicion.
And we need to even be suspicious of our suspicions and, you know, et cetera.
Exactly.
And, again, it's not like, it's not like at the end of that, like, we get to the best orientation.
It's like, I mean, you can't guarantee anything within that dynamic of suspicion.
There's nothing guaranteed or there's no comfort.
So, again, it's like, right, like, Nathaniel, you're saying, there's no, I'm not, I'm both critiquing these resting points that people glom onto.
But you also have to articulate those as basically necessary moments of discourse or at least, like, understandable.
Like, right, you can diagnose them within this movement.
Because everybody needs to territorialize in Deleuze's terms.
It's just that once you reify that one of those moments, that's where I find there to be trouble.
Well, so it's not just the delusion that one has found rest.
That is more profoundly you're criticizing the drive or the desire to find the rest.
Right.
We want what's bad for us.
We want what's going to kill us.
There's the death drive.
Right.
We want to arrest the process of becoming.
Yeah.
Well, it's just such a strange, like, when you really think about it, because it's like you both need those resting points and you also can't have a final one.
Because, like you're saying, it would be death.
So the death drive is precisely the suspension of any final resting point, for Freud at least, right?
So it's like that.
Again, you probably can't think of it in points, but it does kind of lend itself to that.
Where, like, you have a, you have a, you have a territorialization and then you destroy it and then you bring, you bring yourself to a new one.
It's clearly not linear like that, but, but this is the, like, the language of de-territorialization, like, nothing is ever territorialized, right?
It's only the process of.
Nothing is ever a-territorialized.
Exactly.
Right, exactly.
And I think that's, you know, I, you know, I think that you can definitely say in this Hegelian sense that there is always, you know, a, the, the, the production of, or there is the process of resting, right?
Or, like, or arresting, right?
But it's, it never stabilizes into a point and, man, do people want it.
And that's, that should be the thing that we have to relentlessly combat and be on guard against.
Right.
Because even logically, that stability lends itself to death.
Like, just within the system, you can't access that stability.
Yeah.
That stasis is untenable.
And, yeah, for some fucking weird reason, people want it.
You have to do a lot of work to maintain things as they are.
It's never just, right.
Which is, I always use the language of, of, you know, the closest you can get to that stability is cancer, right?
Which is the constant laborious reproduction of the same, which is never quite the same, and it takes over everything, right?
That even, I, that, that to me is the closest, like, the thing that people, people want their own cancer.
They, they, they want to reproduce the condition, like, some kind of ideal condition that in its very repetition is never, ever the same.
But it's, but isn't there a difference between places of rest and places of moral superiority, right?
Like, I mean, to, to me, the idea of rest, I mean, if we're thinking of it in those terms of, like, movement and rest, um, or relative movements or whatever, like, I, I don't have a problem with rest.
I don't have a problem with, like, okay, you can't sprint 24-7, right?
Like, you know, I mean, you can't.
I mean, you've got to, you've got to rest in order to be able to sprint.
Um, but there, there's a difference between that and a lot of what drives, um, the projects that you're talking about isn't so much rest as, like, certainty, right?
Like, the, the, the belief that I have the answer or that I know the solution or correctness in some ways, truth, you would say.
Which is, which, I mean, is kind of a resting.
It's a kind of rest.
Resting in certainty.
Resting in the, the grounds of your system that you set up.
That, see, that's, that's one of the main issues I have with Barad is that even though it's this, like, very strange, diffracted ontology, there's still a grounds to that ontology.
And it's, it's materiality, it's relationality.
And so, she rests in that, right?
She's, she's completely at, at peace with her, uh, with her ontological framework, right?
But the, the idea here is you want to come up with a, a notion of rest then that isn't stable, right?
Like, that, that, so if, you know, what absolute spirit or pure contingency or pure negation or whatever would be a sense of stasis that's not immobile, right?
It's not, it doesn't simply repeat the same and it never could.
It can't even imagine that.
Um, so if, if, if rest then is refigured as a particular style of movement, um, then it would be less, less troubling, right?
And less, and less, um, um, um, it'd be more difficult to, um, uh, for a place like, rest like that to grant anybody certainty.
Because I do agree with Nate that there is a connection between places of rest and places of certainty because certainty would require a certain amount of stability.
Otherwise, that certainty is pretty false, right?
You need to have that, that's that stable ground from which to assert one's certainty.
So, yeah, I, I would say, I, I mean, again, I've, I've always, for whatever reason, I don't have the best ability to articulate, but I always think of this in terms of, of a cancer.
That there is still movement there.
It is still this, um, it is still a kind of change, but, um, and it, and, you know, it looks like a place, it looks like it's just the repetition of the same and there's some kind of stability and staticness there.
But only because there is this relentless reproduction machine going on.
And this is why Derrida is so attractive to me, attractive to me too, because there are virtually no resting places in, in his writing.
I mean, like, there's the critique of his, like, relativism, right?
The kind of, like, lazy, sloppy, like, anything goes in Derrida.
It's not that.
It's just suspicion.
It's self-consciousness is what that is.
Like, what, why is that a bad thing?
It has nothing to do with moral or conceptual relativism.
It's about rigorous scrutiny of your own movement of thinking, you know?
Right.
Well, and this is where, I mean, so for instance, I just, I'm squeamish around terms like rest and movement just because they're so, like, it just, it reminds me so much of years ago.
I mean, when, and I think a lot of people still think this, that the target of sort of postmodern thinking was Descartes and the cogito, right?
Like, I think.
And I just remember learning years ago, like, that's not, the cogito as a place of rest, the I thing, that's not troubling, right?
Like, that's, you know, it lives in its own little quasi-solipsistic universe.
I mean, the danger is the appropriation machine, which is, you know, there's a way in which, and I just always associated this with Hegel, right?
Hegel was, to me, Hegel was the real danger from Enlightenment thinking, not Descartes, insofar as what Hegel often, and by the way, I'm getting this from Adorno's, the negative, the dialectic of Enlightenment, right?
Like, the Odysseus stuff, where, like, the figure for Enlightenment should be Odysseus.
He's the guy who travels around all the foreign lands and kills, you know, like, appropriates the other into a version of the same, like, you know, putting a McDonald's in Red Square and on the moon and, you know, in other words, producing everything of a version of self, right, in that way, as at that form of appropriation.
So that that, so it was never an issue of stability versus movement.
It was always an issue of a movement that simply appropriates or projects itself versus a movement that expropriates, you know, that those differences, to me, were the key differences, you know, so, but in terms of how we're thinking of appropriation here, it's not the McDonald's at Red Square, you know.
It is not simply, I put a version of myself, the self-aliening move of otherness is not just, I make everything into a version of me, it is everything, you know, it's the self-other, mutually, self-transformative function.
Yeah, every appropriation is an expropriation, at least in the way we've been reading this version of Hegel, yeah.
So, it's the lack of comfort there that's appealing, right, like, you're not simply appropriating your environment or the other.
They're just as much affecting you, and there's no, there's no simple difference between the two.
There's no subject-object divide, whereas for Descartes, you know, there obviously was kind of a clean, a clean cut for him.
In Hegel, it's, it becomes indistinguishable to the point of, you could say paralysis in certain cases, but if you reach absolute spirit, it becomes freeing, or liberating in some way, you know.
But I still think you can make distinctions between different styles of appropriation there, where, like, some kinds of appropriation are more inclined to generate difference, and other kinds are less inclined, you know, like, I mean, you know, when I eat, I'm pretty much appropriating it to make myself, yes, of course, there is a change in my body.
You are what you eat, John, you are what you eat.
Right, but that's one, I mean, that's why eating is, to me, eating is an interesting, you know, circumstance to think about appropriation, right, and, and, because it is.
It's like, I'm taking in the other in an incredibly literal way, and what does that do?
Well, it does different kinds of things, right?
I mean, it's not simply, even if we just confine ourselves to that domain of eating, some things make you sick, some things, one pill makes you sick, sorry.
But, you know, there are different types of appropriation, or different ways that different foods, and different, so you have different kinds of appropriation, some of which are more transformative than others, and some of which are more simply self-replicative.
This is what is really interesting to me about disgust in the sort of gustatory register, is, you know, like, our tastes change, and, you know, what we find disgusting, and what, like, we literally want to throw up, or, like, gag at the thought of, changes based on our sort of encounters with, with difference.
And the thing that would, in one context, at one point in my life, make me want to throw up, becomes just a delight in another.
Your favorite suit.
Yeah, exactly, and, you know, I mean, this is a case where, I mean, I don't even think eating is a simple appropriation of the other, that it reorients you to, you know, a whole lot of things, and I, like, you know, in my own, like, development is the wrong word, but the sort of, like, my own cultivation of getting used to different kinds of foods.
It's just, like, you get, you get the hang of a handful of things, and now suddenly a whole array of things come into, like, become possible to experience and engage, and the sort of, the universal, you know, throw up reaction becomes, isn't replaced by some universal enjoyment action, but becomes replaced with this whole heterogeneous field of different kinds of experiences and orientations to things.
And that, you know, that, like, to me, that, there, there's, I feel like I'm, well, okay, that food is all shit now, so, I, I was gonna say that I'm far more expropriated than I, than it is appropriated, but.
Right, right, right.
I'm kind of expropriated, too.
Well, it's, it's transformative, you can certainly say that, I mean.
Yeah.
Right.
But, again, that kind of points to the complexity of the for itself in Hegel, like, where, so, where something was, where something was previously disgusting or made you feel alienated or, like, kind of was scary to you, you can then, at a certain point, you know, revert or transform that thing into a positive experience.
So, like, it's, it's the same as Foucault's, like, you end up fetishizing the oppressor, basically, or, like, the thing, the thing that really scares you, you end up wanting.
Um, and it becomes part of that movement of spirit in, in Hegel's terms.
Like, I think of it with, um, with, like, really dissonant music.
Like, if you showed that to a baby, it's gonna cry.
Um, but you show it to a grad student, and he's gonna be like, ooh, this is really cool, and it's making, you know, my skin tingle, and it's, you know what I mean?
So, like, there's levels of that appropriative function, and it, again, you don't have to think of it, like, as totalizing in this, like, weird, uh, fascistic way, but, again, it's, like, the, the liberatory potential, uh, is, is obscured there.
Whereas, for, for a lot of thinkers, like, that's what they lean into, it's, like, the, the proliferation of desire, whereas, for someone like Hegel, it's, like, we should still be suspicious of that, you know?
Yeah, yeah.
I don't know.
Um.
Yeah, I mean.
Well, I don't know how much this is a response, but, like, I, I was really moved by Hume's sensibility of taste, like, I don't know, 10, 20 years ago.
Like, just, like, I, you know, I first came across it when I was taking an undergrad philosophy of art course, and, you know, just, like, the monotonous repetition of text, that thought that they had, sort of, like, discovered the right metric for determining good art from bad art was just, like, for me, exhausting.
And then, coming across Hume was, like, no, there are, like, bodies cultivate different orientations to, um, to, to food or, or, or, or whatever else it is, and they're not predetermined that, you know, these sorts of, sorts of things are played out in repetitions of, um, of exposure.
And, um, and so I was really excited to teach that to my students a year or two ago.
And my students reacted, like, really violently against it because, like, it was really scary for them to, to think that they're at a bodily level and at a psychological level that, that, um, uh, the stuff that they found repulsive or disgusting could, they could acquire a taste for it.
And that was, in some ways, a major threat to them.
And I think that you're totally right that then, that the other becomes fetishized insofar as it becomes, like, a life, like, the other becomes a life-sustaining thing for me because I'm able to demarcate myself against it and it's got to stay away.
But that, for me, that, like, the, the, the, you know, um, the fear of appropriation is very much so akin to a fear of, of, of, of, yeah, of self-transformation.
Like, I'm going to become it or it's going to become me.
Well, I, I remember, I mean, this is anecdotal, so irrelevant, but I mean, I, I remember, like, six years ago, I just kind of stopped liking the taste of beer.
And, and, and I, I remember when it happened, I mean, it was over the course of, like, a semester and I was just, like, you know, I, I kind of fought through it a few times at the speakeasy and whatever, because, and, and then there was a point where I was just, like, I just don't like drinking beer anymore.
And, like, that's such a central part of who I, how I think of who I am or, or was at the time that it was really kind of traumatic, right?
Like, who am I going to be if I don't like the taste of beer?
I mean, fortunately, I had scotch as a sort of side replacement, but, like, I don't even want to have a beer anymore.
And it's still true today.
Like, I just don't like, and it's not, I didn't have, like, a bad experience or anything like that.
And everything was going along just fine.
And then just a few times I was, like, eh, maybe I had a bad bottle, maybe I had whatever.
And then it was, like, I just don't like this stuff.
And it was, it was very hard to be, like, okay, I'm not, I'm just not a beer drinker anymore.
It's that identification move again.
Yeah.
This also, this sounds like it's also sort of been a part of this whole experiment of, like, what does the subtraction of alcohol do in my life?
Because, I mean, like, you know, the easy, like, the quick way of reading that is to say either you have, you know, your gustatory sensibilities have contracted and you've lost the capacity to appreciate something that's, you know, in and of itself good.
Or you've advanced beyond the vulgar taste of beer and you've gone into something more reified and you've cultivated.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Whatever it is.
But, you know, if you just accept, like, you know, the, the, the, the complex that is, you know, your ton and mouth in beer, like, that's not the, the whole story of liking beer.
That is connected to a whole lot of other things and it just opens up, it closes down some ways of living and it opens up other ones.
And that just becomes a far more interesting way of, of, of imagining that relationship to another.
This thing.
I mean, that's, yeah.
Like I told you, I told you guys when my TV blew up a few weeks ago, you know, and, and I just decided not to replace it.
And I always have the TV on, I very rarely watch it, but it's on a lot, especially with basketball.
And I was absolutely certain.
I'm like, well, I'm going to try this experiment because life presented me with this and I'm going to be a no TV person for a little while.
But I guarantee you I'll have the TV back before the NBA, you know, kicks off.
Two weeks into the NBA, I still don't have a TV, right?
Like, I mean, I've just, I'm, I'm just riding this.
And it was one of those situations that, okay, life presented me with this thing.
It was difficult at first.
I mean, I told you guys, like, I found myself reaching for the remote constantly, but now it's like, okay, my evenings are completely different because I'm not located with, you know, the TV on and the back on.
And when I, like, when I was texting you guys last night, like, I have to go find the game.
I can't just, the game doesn't just come on for me.
I have to make a very specific effort.
So the game that you guys were watching, I couldn't get.
So I went to the other game, you know.
So it's done.
It produces different, it's a transformation.
I mean, habits are so complex and difficult to break.
Like, you can't, you have to re-articulate them.
You can't simply, like, abandon a habit, right?
And so when you disidentify with a habit that's so crucial to your sense of self, I mean, that's disorienting.
Like, I always come back, I always come back to music because it's something I consume compulsively and just way too much.
And it's like, when I no longer, like, there's music where, from a few years ago, used to bring me so much pleasure and certain artists that I just consumed all goddamn day.
And now, after certain changes in my life and those memories of that music are associated with things, right?
Like, I no longer, it's now, like, painful.
So, like, music that I used to love is now I have to, like, reject in some way.
And it's like, it's just such a strange experience where you have to, like, no longer, yeah, consume that.
But I think that to be generous towards the, what I earlier referred to as the kind of dumb liberal appropriations of the broad or whatever else, I think a lot of what they're, what's feeding that is an interest in people just getting okay with their idiosyncratic desires.
And that because so much of the, I mean, this certainly animates Butler for, without question, but others as well, I do think that there is a sense of, like, look, you can just like the things that you like.
And you don't, it doesn't really matter whether that's, you know, heteronormative or whatever, you know, like, just be okay with your desires and with their transformations and mutations and whatever else.
I mean, I do think that that, for instance, Anti-Oedipus, I mean, that's certainly an animating sensibility behind that is, like, just get okay with your desire or with desire and how it operates sort of through you in that regard.
Um, I agree with that if you're kind of adopting this self-conscious orientation that we're all sort of endorsing here, like, where you're not simply just accepting your desires, but you're thinking through them.
Like, you don't have, you don't have to reject them, but, like, you know, you embody them and think about them.
It's the, if you're, like, a simple racist piece of shit, you know, you're not going to tell that person, well, just stay comfortable in that mind space, you're fine.
You know what I mean? So, like, there's more or less, like, harmful desires and habits and attitudes.
But, so I think that's, because I was going somewhere like that as well, and I wasn't thinking of in terms of racism, although it works far better.
I was just thinking of somebody with, like, you know, a wildly restrictive and thereby dangerous diet, right?
Because, just because we were on the food thing.
Uh, but let's go with racism.
But, like, it just seems like there's a difference between desire and comfort, right?
Like, comfort is a particular kind of desire, and comfort tends to almost always be coupled with a fear or desire to push away, you know, the uncomfortable, right?
Which is just, like, the one thing that learning or teaching or experimenting or thinking all are definitely not okay with are comfort.
It's, like, the one thing that they're not particularly okay with in most articulations.
Um, and so, yeah, there's, whether it's self-reflection or consciousness or experimentation or whatever it is, like, some kind of, um, you know, engagement with, with difference, uh, insofar as that would be avoidable anyway, um, like, seems to be a pretty crucial part of the discovery of one's desires.
And the allowance of them to be able to take shape and emerge and, uh, uh, withdraw and, and whatever else.
I, I completely agree, but what's so frustrating for me is that that embracement of difference, which I agree is, like, key for, for theory, for living, for whatever, that gets codified today in people like Barad.
Like, that becomes the resting, that becomes the resting place.
So, it's no longer, experimentation just gets reified into this apparatus, into the liberal progressive apparatus.
And it's, like, I agree with the premise, but you're not actually taking it to the, you're not, you're not turning it over.
I don't know another word.
You're not transforming that, that mode.
Well, it seems like it becomes a moralism insofar as adding this, like, you know, experimenting with difference as akin to finding particular others and differences.
And then forcing myself to enjoy and like them, right?
It's, like, I must learn to like, um, you know, sound, um, art, uh, because this is an other that.
This is the cool, smart, other.
This is the right, smart other, right?
And that's, that doesn't seem to be, that seems to be, you know, making sound art the same.
By saying, ah, this has been codified under this particular category and therefore it's, it's the right kind of other.
But that's, there's nothing new about that.
We've, we've always been down with finding the right others to bring into our, into our sphere.
And that wouldn't be experimentation at all.
That would, like, those, those roads have already been created for us.
Right.
Yeah.
Here's another you have to like, now sushi or, you know, the poke bowl or whatever.
Hybrid cars.
Yeah.
I know.
It's just, it's like people know the terms and they know how they're supposed to function,
but they can't actually get them to do the work that they, not that they should be doing, but that they can do.
You know, because they, because it's difficult to, to, to, to, well, in, in John's words, render the other indistinct,
which is like, this thing has presented itself as other to me.
And I've already codified it as a distinct other.
And it takes work to trouble the, the, um, the forces that render it recognizable.
And if I incorporate it, recognize it, well, yeah, it's still going to do stuff, but, you know, my only real options are like,
I don't have a whole lot of options in terms of experimenting with it.
As long as I know what it is from beginning to end.
Hence the importance of the Russian formalists and defamiliarization.
Mm-hmm.
I, I want to add in one, one other, this is a slightly different tack, but this might be an interesting one.
It might not be.
Um, so Nate a second ago said like, we're all more or less comfortable with this self-consciousness thing.
And I, uh, um, I bristled at that.
Um, and I bristled at my own bristling as a perfect Hegelian response.
Um, and I, and I thought for a moment, I'm like, maybe that's part of the hesitation is that there seems to be, uh, um, well, I go back and forth on this.
So one is the role of consciousness here seems to be quite important and, and quite elevated in a very traditional sort of enlightenment way.
Like consciousness is the thing.
And, and I, and, and I, I recognize and accept your, I mean, so on the one hand I kind of go, well, hey, that's kind of an interesting move today because the intellectual climate is not one that thinks consciousness is relevant at all.
In fact, the basis for all the new materialism stuff is who gives a fuck about consciousness?
Let's just talk about stuff doing things.
Yeah.
Um, and then I'm like, well, you know, I see what criticism, self-criticism, relentless self-criticism gets in terms of the movement.
And I was like, well, can't you have self-criticism without consciousness?
Like, does it have to involve conscious thought?
Like, can't it involve it?
I'm not talking about unconscious thought, which certainly, you know, but I'm talking to like, can't your body just react to your body as a criticism?
Like, for instance, when something makes you nauseous, isn't that a criticism, um, of the thing that you have incorporated, right?
Like, it doesn't, it doesn't necessarily require a conscious awareness of my nausea or of anything whatsoever.
Like, can't we, is it possible to think criticism as the kind of movement of negation without consciousness being the necessary engine for, uh, the criticism?
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Yes.
Absolutely.
I mean, this is, for me, what's been interesting.
I haven't been thinking about this in terms of criticism explicitly, but in terms of thinking, and I, like, especially in writing this Plato piece, you know, trying to think of reading or thinking as, as writing, not mediated through writing, but writing is thinking in so far as writing is, and I'll have to be, forgive me for this term for just a second, but like, um, writing is nothing more than self-exteriorization, which is, like, writing puts out
What a mark that, or is the putting out a mark that, or is the putting out of a mark that has to, that is put into a new chain that provokes some kind of differential response, which then puts out a new mark that puts out, that has a different response to the chain that it's been inserted within.
And to me, that movement is nothing more than thinking, and you could then subdivide that movement, and, like, you know, like, this one got rejected, or this one got dismissed, or didn't get taken up, and that's a kind of criticism, or that's a kind of whatever else it is.
But that doesn't have to, I mean, that certainly does happen within the realm of, of consciousness that we, as we typically describe it, but it's not in any way, uh, driven by it.
Driven by it, or exclusive to it.
Yeah.
I mean, I've been thrown around self-consciousness, uh, loosely here, as, like, the good thing, mostly because that's how Hegel frames it.
I was gonna say, that's, it's not you, it's Hegel.
I mean, Hegel's very much, but I, I mean, the way, I'm not even really thinking about consciousness, basically, I'm just thinking about, like, it would almost be, the more accurate term for me would be self-interrogation.
So, consciousness doesn't have to be, like, a separate thing from the body, or whatever, it's, it's a suspicion of consciousness, right, that, that Hegel's kind of endorsing.
It's not, like, a, it's not a reifying or essentializing of consciousness itself, it's talking about the limits of it, and just trying to, sort of, get at the, you know, the details of the movement of thinking, which includes bodily, affective, uh, thinking as well, so.
But, but, but doesn't, though, I mean, that's, that's, that's actually a real complication in terms of the, because sense certainty, I mean, I know we haven't read that thing, but, I mean, that seems like the kind of primordial, you know, like, like, uh, the early, the early phases, you know, and so, I, I believe that one could do the work on thinking to distinguish it from consciousness and to have a kind of materiality of it.
But, but it does seem to me like it would require work, because here it does seem like it's, it's that, that's the animal, you know, or, or, or the sort of subhuman or not, not evolved enough human, um, position.
So, that, that might be another hinge of, of, of questioning, possibly.
Right.
And so, it's not your, I mean, you know, your use of the term self-consciousness is one that, for the most part, I just don't even, I'm like, yeah, I get it.
And, and I'm obviously, like, there's a way in which I do have an investment in consciousness, but interestingly enough, for me, I feel like my investment in consciousness is as an epiphenomenon, meaning it's like, oh, it's so cool that that thing happened in my head, right?
Like, I, I really, like, that's how I experience my thinking, you know, and even when my thinking is this sort of, like I said, sort of following the Hegelian chain of negation, it's like, oh, it's so cool that I've, you know, internalized this thing such that my thinking even manifested.
And, so, I, but I don't think of my thinking as driving it entirely.
In all fairness, of course, I think my thinking can, in certain instances, drive my actions.
I think that it, it does, but I don't think it does that all the time at all.
Right.
I mean, I, I feel like most of the time, thinking happens to me, right?
Or thinking happens through me.
Like, I get caught up in a particular kind of chain, and because there are already a handful of chains going on here, weird permutations happen.
And something comes out of it, and then it might, you know, it might be bouncing between something more or less called me and a bunch of other things more or less in my proximity.
Yeah.
But, like, that, like, I feel like I'm caught up in that process rather than the engine of that process.
And, in fact, I feel like my thinking suffers.
Yeah.
Like, I feel like my thinking suffers the most.
Yes.
Right.
Exactly.
My thinking suffers the most when I try to do it.
And I'm like, all right, step one, step two.
When you make me fucking read it, it's even worse.
Exactly.
But, right, you kind of have to give way to that, right?
It's not, like, I'm not going to say it's not natural, but, like, you have to sort of facilitate that a little bit.
So, it's not that you're the motor of self-consciousness, but you kind of have to allow that to happen in some way, even if it's implicit.
I don't think most people allow for that, right?
I agree.
And there's, I mean, I've always thought of it as, like, one of the things that I'm interested in facilitating as a teacher is production of increased surface area.
And surface area means capacity to be affected, right, in the Spinoza sense.
It's exposure, meaning, like, if your average person on a particular issue has very, very narrow capacity for exposure, what are some other things that can make them affected more, like, that can increase that?
Surface area, again, I just think in biological viral metaphorics in that regard of, like, what are ways of, to me, this is rhetoric, right?
Like, what are the ways of producing the possibility of infection?
And you have to, and again, by the way, it relates to our previous conversation because one of the very important strategies that viruses use is non-recognition, indistinguishability.
Because the moment that it's recognized, then you have, like, you know, T cells and the immuno response and whatever, whatever.
So, you know, the effective virus that may well be our DNA, the effective viruses are the ones that are not recognized at all as viruses.
You know, and so that's the sense of indistinguishability as a condition for generativity of whatever, like, you know, of transformation.
And that's the key is that, you know, I mean, if you're thinking of rhetoric in its instrumental senses, then, you know, you want the infection to be for the sake of something.
And, like, to me, that's a battery to viruses.
The viruses don't, you know, want the destruction of the cell.
No, no, no.
I don't even think they want the propagation of future virus cells.
Like, they just express their difference.
And when they express it, like, when that difference is expressed in the combination of the virus and cell, like, one kind of thing happens.
And, yes, the death of the cell is often that thing or the hijacking of the cell or whatever else it is.
But, you know, the surface area is for the sake of the transformation.
And then it takes a second level of judgment to be able to say that that is a bad transformation or a good transformation.
But the impulse is to trap that virus and not allow it to run its course, right?
At least in terms of, like, I'm thinking just in terms of consciousness.
Like, when you have flights of thinking that are more or less incoherent, most people's coping strategy is to territory-like, to latch on to something, right?
Whether it's a, I need to watch a movie or I need to, like, get out of my head somehow.
I need to listen to a podcast.
But if you take a step back and, like, just allow the self to mediate rather than to explicitly mediate or glom on to something,
that's when you can actually achieve something productive with that movement rather than stifling it, you know?
I need to quick, the more you know time out, that word glom that you use a lot, a lot, I don't, I mean, I get what you're saying.
Is it the wrong word?
Yeah, latch.
I'm just curious, like, where it comes from or, like, you know, is it just a word that, well, is it, like, biological?
You know, I started saying it because I was saying latch on too much.
So, are there any other terms that I can circulate?
Because I'm finding, when I listen back, I'm like, man, I'm saying certain things a lot.
So, I'm, like, looking for...
You need to diversify your portfolio?
You guys listen to yourself in the re-listening more.
I listen to you guys in the re-listening.
Yeah, only me.
I only listen to my takes.
I'm like, I just go right to my portion.
I'm like, oh, that's great.
Listen to me.
I'm so...
It was...
Like, I don't think there's anything wrong with the term or that you use it too much.
It's just, like, a term that is unfamiliar with me and I'm just, I'm always an entomology nerd.
And I'm like, where does that word come from?
It's familiar to me, Nate.
It's...
I mean, I never thought twice of it, so...
Yeah, I have no idea.
Just to latch on or to grab on or glom on, I've always...
I mean, I get the sense of it.
Like, I...
Like, I didn't...
It didn't throw me for a loop.
Like, what does that...
What the hell does it mean to glom on?
My goal...
My goal for next podcast is to say neither glom on nor latch on.
I'm going to try not to say either of those things.